<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Classes_taughts | James Watling</title>
    <link>https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Classes_taughts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jwatling.github.io/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Classes_taughts</title>
      <link>https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conservation Biology</title>
      <link>https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/bl_419/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/bl_419/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHeck out some of the social media campaigns developed by students in this class in SPring 2021 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/jcu_ocean_acidification/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/rethinkcoalmining/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 4.5 billion years of Earth history, there have never been an many species on the planet as there was until about 10,000 years ago. In just a geological blink of an eye, humans have become a major threat to species around the world. Starting with the extinction of the Ice Age mammals, which was almost certainly due at least partly to overhunting by humans, and accelerating in the past few hundred years, and particularly the past few decades, humans have created the leading edge of what will likely be a sixth mass extinction event. In this class, we will talk about the kinds of things that humans do to cause species to go extinct, why some kinds of species are more extinction-prone than others, and what kinds of things we can do to avert the worst of the extinction crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This class will be a mix of typical lecture, discussions, hands-on demos with the kinds of software conservation biologists use, and guest lectures from speakers from around the world. Your big project in class will be a digital science communication campaign on a conservation topic of your choice. You&amp;rsquo;ll be able to choose the medium you work in (video, podcast, social media), define a target audience, and roll out your campaign as the semester progresses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental Earth Science</title>
      <link>https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/ph-115/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/ph-115/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&#34;https://jwatling.github.io/uploads/PH115%20Podcast.mp3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; to listen to one of the student podcasts on environmental consequences of meat consumption&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an introductory course that assumes no prior knowledge of geology. We are going to spend the next 15 weeks learning about the five Earth spheres: the geosphere (the solid Earth, comprised of minerals and rocks), hydrosphere (liquid water), cryosphere (solid water&amp;ndash;ice), atmosphere (water vapor), and the biosphere (living species). How many of those spheres do you see in the picture above from the tepuis, or tabletop mountains in Venezuela?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some degree we will talk about the spheres separately, but one of the things I really want you to get from this course is that those spheres are linked in really important ways. We will pay special attention to links between one element of the biosphere (the human population) and the other Earth spheres. Geology influences our lives in hugely consequential ways&amp;ndash;think fossil fuels, global climate, agriculture, natural hazards&amp;ndash;and that&amp;rsquo;s just the beginning! By the end of this semester you will be able to recognize the most common rocks and minerals, infer the environment where they formed, understand how hose rocks and minerals were molded by plate tectonics to create geological landforms, articulate how the solid Earth influences climate, see how water and other matter flow through the Earth system, and appreciate how all the elements of the Earth system influence humans. It&amp;rsquo;s a big task, but I promise we will get there together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course is divided into eight modules of about two weeks each. Each class is focused on a particular topic that feeds into the overarching module. Before most classes students will be asked to do some reading and watch lecture and other videos online. These readings and videos are the primary source of foundational knowledge, like key vocabulary and important concepts. Think of those videos and readings as homework&amp;ndash;students focus on those outside of class, and come equipped to each class meeting armed with their new knowledge base. In class, we will apply that new knowledge in different ways&amp;ndash;sometimes we will use problem sets, other times a short activity, or a discussion. Class will also be a time to ask questions and clarify points of confusion. We will also use the Canvas discussion boards as a venue for Q &amp;amp; A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;our signature assignment (the big one worth the most points!) in PH 115 will be a geology-themed podcast that you produce on a topic of your choice. All scientists communicate their work in different formats. Traditionally, the three primary formats were journal articles, poster presentations, and scientific talks. Those formats are very focused on communicating science to other scientists. That’s an important skill to have, for sure. But communicating science to non-scientists is important too—now more than ever. Science communication is in high demand. Your challenge in this assignment is to create an engaging, informative podcast targeted at a non-expert audience. This is an opportunity to not only learn a lot about a particular topic, but actually create new content for other people to learn from. Along the way, you will develop some science communication skills, and leave this class with a tangible product that you can talk about and share when applying for internships and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to GIS</title>
      <link>https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/bl_417/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/bl_417/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&#34;https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/ca8b24ec66ca4e7f86c7e7260f4c95cc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/32fbba15d4c346b0afc70e7996b6c16e&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/9cda1352b3384af6a7f6919c0b617156&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see story maps created by students in this class in Spring 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an introductory course, but one that will be different from most other courses you&amp;rsquo;ve taken. Our focus this semester is on the analysis of spatial data using specialized software for mapping and analysis. If you think about it, pretty much any kind of question you would ask about the world has a spatial component to it. The natural world (including the human footprint) is exceedingly variable, and that variation is often not that random. Being near a river makes it more likely your house will flood than if you are far from a river. Animal populations are denser in some areas, but not in others. Even our political idealogy is developing a spatial component as we segregate into red states and blue states. This semester will be all about learning how to think about and quantify those kinds of spatial differences in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This class is going to be a lot of work, and it&amp;rsquo;s going to a different kind of work than you are probably used to. We will be at the computer using the ArcGIS software package for virtually every class meeting. You&amp;rsquo;ll use lots of other types of software as well, and spend tons of time figuring out how to make the software work. I&amp;rsquo;m going to guide you as best I can, but you are definitely going to have to put in some serious time outside of class getting comfortable with the software. At some point we are all going to get stuck on something. It&amp;rsquo;s important we are all patient with ourselves and each other. I guarantee you that at some point you are going to want to throw your computer out the window, and me along with it. Please don&amp;rsquo;t, but also know that that is normal. If you need to, take a few minutes, clear your head, and try again. I will never knowingly ask you to do something in class that can&amp;rsquo;t be done-everything I ask you to do is do-able. If something is not working, think about possible reasons why, and take a different approach. It may take a few tries, but you will figure it out. Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to ask other students or myself for help. We will all need it at some point-and I guarantee that I will be asking you for help over the course of the semester as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that if you make a serious effort to learn these skills, you will have some highly marketable skills by the end of this semester. Multiple students have taken this class with no previous experience, and gone on to jobs where GIS was a big component of their work. You should absolutely put this on your CV and use the work you do in class as a talking point on job interviews in the future. No one is going to be unimpressed with your software and quantitative spatial analysis skills, I promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major part of your grade in the class will be based on your capstone project: an original story map that you design and publish. You will be responsible for identifying a question you wish to answer or an issue you will address using your new GIS skills. Several landmarks over the course of the semester will keep you on track towards the completion of a 10 minute oral presentation and a ~ 2500 word story map at the end of the course. I&amp;rsquo;ve given you a couple example story maps already, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazonteam.org/storytelling-maps/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here is a link to some others&lt;/a&gt; that are really well done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your story map is about combining visual and text-based content in a compelling and accessible way. With that in mind, you definitely want to be thinking about incorporating strong visuals, including photos and original maps that you create. But I also want you to be doing some analysis in this project, not just making maps. Think of this as a research paper, but in a digital, story map format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will build your story map using a template in ArcGIS online. You can link to the story maps webpage &lt;a href=&#34;https://storymaps.arcgis.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and click sign in. You&amp;rsquo;ll have to sign up for an account the first time you login. This is free and easy. Once you do that, you can start creating a new story. There is a good tutorial &lt;a href=&#34;https://learn.arcgis.com/en/projects/share-the-story-of-an-expedition/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that goes through the process of creating a story map.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Principles of Biology III</title>
      <link>https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/bl_159/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jwatling.github.io/classes_taught/bl_159/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check out a couple of example podcasts from Fall 2020 &lt;a href=&#34;https://jwatling.github.io/uploads/final%20podcast.mp3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://jwatling.github.io/uploads/BL%20159%20Podcast.mp3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt; here &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an introductory course that builds from what students have learned about sub-organismal biology (Principles I) and organismal biology (Principles II). We spend 15 weeks surveying the diversity of life on Earth, and the evolutionary processes that have generated the tremendous biological diversity that surrounds us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spend quite a bit of time talking about traits that define clades - broad groups of species evolved from a common ancestor. But what I really want students to get from this course is an understanding for how much humans rely on biodiversity for our well-being. Biodiversity influences our lives in profound ways-it is the source of every single calorie every human has ever consumed, it is a largely unexplored source of medicine, and it inspires consumer products that we all use (velcro was invented to mimic the way plant seeds attach to your pants when you walk through the woods). Humans also have an innate sense of biophilia, or affinity for nature: US national parks receive the equivalent of the entire country&amp;rsquo;s population in visits per year, and more Americans visit zoos and aquariums than attend all professional sporting events combined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course is divided into seven modules of about two weeks each. Each class is focused on a particular topic that feeds into the overarching module. Before most classes students are asked to do some reading and watch lecture and other videos online. These readings and videos are the primary source of foundational knowledge, like key vocabulary and important concepts. Think of those videos and readings as homework&amp;ndash;students focus on them outside of class, and come equipped to each class meeting armed with their new knowledge base. In class, we apply that new knowledge in different ways&amp;ndash;sometimes we will use problem sets, other times a short activity, or a discussion. Class is also a time to ask questions and clarify points of confusion. We also use the Canvas discussion boards as a venue for Q &amp;amp; A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The signature assignment (the big one worth the most points!) in BL 159 is a biodiversity-themed podcast that students produce on a topic of their choice. All scientists communicate their work in different formats. Traditionally, the three primary formats were journal articles, poster presentations, and scientific talks. Those formats are very focused on communicating science to other scientists. That’s an important skill to have, for sure. But communicating science to non-scientists is important too—now more than ever. Science communication is in high demand. The challenge in this assignment is to create an engaging, informative podcast targeted at a non-expert audience. This is an opportunity to not only learn a lot about a particular topic, but actually create new content for other people to learn from. Along the way, students develop some science communication skills, and leave this class with a tangible product that they can talk about and share when applying for internships and jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
